welcome back to APUSH in under 3 minutes
no time for intros let's get into it
topic 4.3 starts talking about tensions
in the US economy and differing
viewpoints some war broke out between
Britain and the US in 1812 caused by
British supporting Native American
tribes and impressment on American
Sailors it ended in a draw with the
Treaty of G that the US saw as a win
mostly because of the nationalism caused
by the Battle of New Orleans during this
war Federalists met at the Hartford
Convention discussing disapproval of the
war in potential secession after America
quote unquote won this war this
convention would lead to the party's and
that leads into the introduction of a
man who lots of people don't like
including me Henry Clay this guy was a
lawyer Secretary of State leader of a
future political party and so
influential in this period he introduced
something known as the American system
this was a response to the War of 1812
and suggested to provide National
Economic growth by establishing a
protective tariff creating a national
bank and funding internal improvements
like roads and canals this was so
controversial and caused many debates to
arise from the Democratic Republicans
later known as the Democrats who opposed
it and the new National Republic an
later known as the wigs who supported it
the Supreme Court had its say with its
molok the Maryland case which
established that Federal power Trump's
state power but who cares about that
it's time to talk about early Civil War
causes so throughout the Early Republic
States kept getting added and became
either a slave or free state as this
continued in 1819 there was a bounce of
11 slave states and 11 free states but
as America was expanding Westward
Missouri was added as a state the South
wanted it to be a slave state and it
ended up becoming one the north however
felt cheated and made the Missouri
Compromise which added Maine as an
official free state and said above a
certain line there couldn't be any more
slave states this shows the start of
weak compromises creating tension upon
tension until eventual war and how about
even more Civil War causes the
protective Tariff of 1828 put aack on
imported goods and the South was very
mad at it even to the point they called
it the Tariff of Abominations this led
to the South Carolina exposition and the
Nullification Crisis where the South
openly protested the Tariff they're
likely would have been War if it wasn't
for khone and Clay who proposed the
Tariff of 1833 which would lower the tax
over the years but what this shows is
the South can and will Revolt if it
doesn't like something foreshadowing the
eventual Civil War on the screen now are
some AP style questions for this
topic I'll put the answers on the screen
now I'm starting to realize I need to
advertise my social medias and other
channel at the end of these videos so
please help me out if nothing else at
least go follow the Instagram I know you
and everyone have Instagram so come on
oh and bye-bye